[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, it's not only one question.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's, uh, there's more three questions.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of basic.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I don't think it's like, actually, it's not an answer question, but then I would like to speak a little bit about what actually I'm aiming towards, what I would like you to speak about.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the question is, what is the impermanent nature of six senses?
[SPEAKER_02]: Definition of
[SPEAKER_02]: Why I'm asking is because, you know, as regards external six sense bases, it seems almost like obvious that they are impermanent because they come and go within the range of our experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: But still, I feel that it would be good if you can actually explain what are even these external sense bases, because I already noticed by listening to your talks that you can actually look at things from some unusual perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if it looks obvious what is sound or what is form, visual form, maybe you can actually offer a little bit of something, some
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, the whole life, you live with this ear, or this eye,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it seems that they are always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how to actually, eh, directly see these things, eh?
[SPEAKER_02]: Not only indirectly, like, you know, contemplating, eh, before you go to fall, when you're down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yes, that would work.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But not that, eh, sensual insight, if you work in sensual explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I would like more of this phenomenology, so that they're always there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, let me start then with the first bit, with the six internal bases, which we then...
[SPEAKER_03]: I think it will make obvious what I mean, or make apparent, or at least clearer, what I mean when we're talking about it, when it talks about the external ones, because they're actually not.
[SPEAKER_03]: The external counterparts, in a sense, basically the external objects, are not actually easier to see as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the common misconception of what the external world is, and then people assume that, oh, yeah, this is ever-changing and impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not actually even on the level of the external sense base seen properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the external object, sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the internal, the six internal bases, basically, well, in a most practical approach, that's where your body is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can divide it into six.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can say the eyes, the nose, the ears, the tongue, the body has a sense of touch, and then the mind gets, obviously, separated from the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can pin it down to brain, or you can pin it down to anything more particular.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is, when body, there is mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: When there is no body, the mind cannot remain standing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in that sense, basically,
[SPEAKER_03]: What you need to see on a practical level is that learning how to see the body rightly would sort of reveal the whole sixfold sense base seen properly as impermanent and eventually as that which cannot be taken as so.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, for the practical approach, basically, what you need to see is that you can't take up those senses or you can't take up the body, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's structurally impossible to own it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't access it and make it yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not knowing that, you assume it's yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can't... you don't know that actually, no, actually, this cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you know that the phenomenon of mind, that something belongs to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, these things are impenetrable to that, and you can't own them.
[SPEAKER_03]: But not knowing that sufficiently enough, you own them, just through that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you want to see the impermanence, you don't need any explanation in terms of, like, a previous life and this future life.
[SPEAKER_03]: All you need to see is that that which has already arisen, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: your body, your six senses, precedes you, precedes your sense of ownership, precedes your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: And by preceding means, oh, it comes first, I come second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, I cannot be the master of it, because if I'm the master of something, I come first.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that which you think comes first, actually comes second.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that which you think comes second, actually comes first.
[SPEAKER_03]: And by dwelling just on that, accurately enough, you would stop regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, by... literally, by default, by simply by not regarding the internal things based as yours, and everything else that depends upon them, you won't be able to regard as yours either.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means you won't be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But this is like the anatta aspect.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it seems that it's always anatta comes after understanding properly anicca.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it comes after in a sense of... in a structural sense, not after in the sense of time.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the same insight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anicca, dukkha, is simultaneous insight of anatta on the level of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you see that that upon which your sense of self depends cannot be yours, that sense of self is not yours either.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what anatta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the sense of self that depends upon a six-fold base, or the body,
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how it's come, taken.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the self is assumed priority, and then the self owns these senses, owns this body, and operates with them.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's because there's no wisdom in regards to senses, and it's not seen that actually these senses arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body is given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just find it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You find your eyes.
[SPEAKER_03]: You find the world revealed by your eyes, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if that's understood, then this self, that depends upon that body,
[SPEAKER_03]: Cannot be on, because this is seen as impossible to access in terms of that ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, anicca and dukkha automatically means it felt like anatta, simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not one, two, three, in terms of, ah, first you see anicca, then you spend two or three days thinking about dukkha, then you spend two or three days thinking about anatta.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you see anicca properly, that's what dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that experience as a whole, will not be the experience of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there is no room for the appropriation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can one, like, practice it, you know, like, during your day, you just remind yourself this understanding?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is this the practice?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it is to begin with, but then it has to become more accurate, in a sense of, you actually... you have to be able to see what that phenomenon of the body, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: of the six sense base is, in your present experience, without having to analyze it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Without having to keep repeating what you read, ah, the eye is this, the nose is this, you just... when you see it, you see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But probably in the beginning you mean?
[SPEAKER_03]: In the beginning, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, that's what I've been talking about.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think maybe I didn't... we didn't upload them yet, but in the last few talks, it was basically that any sort of contemplation you do cannot be just based on your thinking as it is now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that thinking as it is now is fully affected by ignorance and by wrong views.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, which means, even if you get the right instructions, you'll be applying them along the wrong lines.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to begin to learn how to think properly, phenomenologically.
[SPEAKER_03]: And thinking properly means seeing things properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because thoughts are images that are being seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you begin that by starting every contemplation or any sort of reasoning, even, on the basis of mindfulness, of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't just kind of go into mystical awe, or like, you know, including the experience as a whole and just stay in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that's just the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're mindful of the experience, you're mindful of the situation, you're mindful if your body's seated in this room, feeling certain mood, feeling certain feelings, having certain perceptions, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, without losing the sight of that, you begin to think.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, then, the contemplation does not become like a like a mental fabrication into obstruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: It becomes more of a practice of discernment.
[SPEAKER_03]: Practice of discernment.
[SPEAKER_03]: Practice of basically looking into, or rather finding things that you've been hearing about in this which is in front of you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that which is in front of you is that which is revealed through that mindfulness of your situation and experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, what I'm saying is, things you want to contemplate, you don't want to contemplate on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want to find those things as already there in that experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means you need to learn how to be properly mindful of the experience, so that these things can be discerned within that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because feeling is already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: All the six senses, depending on what approach you take, all of the six senses are already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't need to think about six senses, and then explain to yourself what they are.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just need to see them as they are, right there, while you're thinking about them.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that can be done only on the basis of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where mindfulness always comes first.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why you can't have too much of the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: But without that mindfulness, no amount of precise instruction or anything like that can make much of a difference, because you just start on the wrong basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can we say that mindfulness is like establishing the working field on which you work?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But even that mindfulness needs to be sort of recognized as if coming from the situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not coming from you and your intention to be mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is it also dependent on conditions?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it something also which can be without this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just, obviously, in the beginning, whatever you intend, whatever you directed attention in your mind, it's sort of assumed as rooted in the Self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why the mindfulness is quite impersonal, even for the Self of you.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's a necessary base.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a kind of semi-neutral base from which you can go the other way, the right way.
[SPEAKER_03]: But without it, you can't possibly go the right way, because you're immediately already in the wrong tracks, tracks of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you try to get the mindfulness as strong as possible, in a sense of as clear, as non-interfering, as wise as possible, so that then the other tracks, tracks of non-self, can be recognized.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that just takes practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is it like to see that the whole situation... Well, again, now you're trying to kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Put the whole situation in front of you.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, as I said, you find yourself in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, instead of trying to put things in front of you, you step back into them, because you are already in them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are already in a situation, whether you want to be or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are always in a situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why the four foundations of mindfulness, one of the main things is that four postures of the body, because you're always in a posture of the body, which is a kind of a symbol.
[SPEAKER_03]: For a situation, you're seated while ta-ta-ta.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're walking while something else.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're lying down, you're standing, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, those things are not just some some weird kind of psychological sort of meditation methods.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, they're phenomena.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're kind of rooting you back into a situation that you cannot escape from.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, you recognize your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just like a small movement of time, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which, on the background, maybe you just... or maybe you just recognize the background.
[SPEAKER_02]: The background, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That makes you arsitic.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not non-verbal.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to think much about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just make this movement of mind to realize.
[SPEAKER_03]: To include.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just to include.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't need to exclude anything that's in front of you now.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you just want to include more than what's in front of you now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's not enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you include that background, because that background, which is your situation,
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, if you include it long enough, with the proper instruction, it becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you realize you have no say even in what's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can only have things in front of you based on the background, based on the situation that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, if you have no eyes, if there are no forms to be seen, wanting sights, having desire towards sights, intentions towards sights, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yet, that's something that's completely taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why many people think they understood the suttas, because, as you can see, it makes sense perfectly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, sure, if there are no eyes, I couldn't see.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if you were to truly understand that, you'd be free from any desire in regard to the domain of sight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anything ever seen, anything ever that would be seen, you'd be almost an anāgāmī, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, why is that not happening then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you realize, ah, so this understanding, so to speak, it's actually understanding only if it's seen in proper terms, on its own terms, not on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It seems that nature is not understanding at all, because if it is... Well, it depends what you want to use.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you want to use the word understanding for, like, kind of intellectual sort of making sense, then, yeah, this is more than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I think you can still use the same word understanding, because you share the same nature of something being understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just not sufficient understanding.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can understand things intellectually, and then you can take it further.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you realize, okay, well, understanding, if done rightly, should free me from suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: My intellectual understanding is not freeing me from suffering, so I need to take it further.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you, I mean, you can take it further by making further abstraction of your intellect, but that's not going to make any difference, and you will know that soon enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, you take it further, basically, by kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Taking it deeper, or taking it backwards, so to speak, by spreading it about, by sort of... well, by making it pertain to the roots of your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why it's kind of... yoniso manasikāra comes always as one of the main factors.
[SPEAKER_03]: The right instruction and that kind of root attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yoniso means womb, so going back to the very origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not origin in terms of the explanation, like 16 lifetimes ago I've done such and such thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: The origin of your present situation, which is your given body, seated there, the form of it, the feelings that are simultaneously present with that, the perception, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think, in body, you can see the difference of the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be also intellectual understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it can be deeper.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then comes pañña.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that's wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pañña is wisdom, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, the practice can be summarized, like, as much as you can to do this movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: To go back to the to the mindfulness, to see this root of your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can see, basically, why... Well, I hope you can see, because many people talk about mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not, you know, it's not a new thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you could see how often it tends to be either mystified or sort of played down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mystified, in a sense, when you hear the teachings often,
[SPEAKER_03]: for the monks or for the other kind of other teachers and other religions, but kind of all says the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, you can just be present here and now, aware of your body and your mind, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where the calming is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's actually, you can see, like, that's what's the goal for them.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you can see, if you actually do it rightly from the suttas, that should be only the very first step.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's like that working field on the issues that I'm looking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because, you know, I...
[SPEAKER_03]: But people, people have a view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like
[SPEAKER_03]: If they don't know that they are supposed to look for something, then they'll inevitably, automatically mystify their experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even if they do the Buddhist mindfulness, they'll mystify it, because they'll just be, you know, expecting it to teach them and to show them the reality or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to basically discern.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why it's so hard.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can see how, if a wrong instruction is given, or if a right instruction hasn't been sufficiently understood, you won't see it, because you don't know what you're supposed to see.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can we actually say, you know, some people, they say that actually just mindfulness is enough in that sense, that it, when you practice it, other things reveal by themselves.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the other things will be revealed by themselves only if you already have a basis of wisdom and a criteria of the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, if you're a sotāpanna, then all you have to do is keep staying mindful and virtuous, and then things will become clear-clear, because you already have that knife that's cutting automatically, you just have to keep directing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But for putujana, it needs to be more than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mindfulness is equal, as I said.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of the most neutral aspect of the experience, of the revealing situation, but it still comes from the angle of putujana.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it cannot miraculously or spontaneously just tip over and become a right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to make it so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so you need the instruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, I was contemplating that if you go, like, for these retreats, you can spend weeks or months practicing mindfulness, but without not much results.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, it's like a question.
[SPEAKER_02]: How, actually, how many thousands of hours you need to do this to move
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can see, as you've just seen yourself, when you're sort of trying to comprehend what I was saying, like, even with the right instruction now, ah, you're supposed to step back.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can do that in an overly controlling manner.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I'm stepping back.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is my situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you are actually over-intending it, which means you're not really stepping back.
[SPEAKER_03]: Means the craving of your sense of self, of your intentionality, it's taking over.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's something that will inevitably happen, and you just have to keep it in check.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, sort of, tune, fine-tune that attitude of stepping in, without over-intending it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you know... Because if you over-intend the background, it becomes that which you intend in the foreground.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means then, at that time, something else is that background that you're not seeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it also is actually quite difficult to grasp.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's so easily misunderstood.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why all the meditation techniques and stuff, they might be repeating these same things, but they do it with this kind of controlling manner, watching, touching, observing, observing, observing, all on the terms of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what remains rooted in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, if you do step in, sometimes, rightly, into that background without, sort of, over-intending it, then you don't know what you're supposed to look for.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you tend to mystify it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you glorify that experience, but it's equally effective in a vijja, as it was before.
[SPEAKER_03]: It had potential for understanding.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you were to have instructions that you can use to discern what's supposed to be discerned, but without that, you won't.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just cannot.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, it's still good to learn how to keep stepping, because eventually,
[SPEAKER_03]: Say that working field has been developed properly, expanded, spread about more and more, even without the right instruction, then you're going to need very little instruction eventually, because you were used to the right proper stepping into the situation, familiarize yourself with it, became established in it, and then the Buddha can just tell you, ah, in the scene, let there just be the scene, and that can be enough for you, because you've already done the actual work.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just needed the last, sort of, drop off.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, of course, yeah, I should have looked at it like that, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, obviously, people, kind of, are not quite there, either, when they begin.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they, sort of, you have to be developing both.
[SPEAKER_03]: Privifying the instruction as much as you can.
[SPEAKER_03]: Making a sense out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not just reading it for inspiration, poetic value, or scholastic merit.
[SPEAKER_03]: Reading because you want to understand.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, simultaneously, developing your mind in terms of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the establishment of mindfulness that sort of reaches a certain strength.
[SPEAKER_03]: And samādhi means composure, being composed.
[SPEAKER_03]: That field of working field, it remains composed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Throughout the day, throughout the situations, throughout the circumstances, it remains composed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind is in samādhi.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind is composed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you can say the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: But because of the, as I said, because of this kind of tend to mystify things, even the plain mindfulness people mystify, then you start having, eh, sort of views of such nature.
[SPEAKER_03]: Views of, like, eh, that experience will teach you the... it's not about the novelty, it's about the new experience that you never experienced, you must be the reality behind and so on and on top of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you end up building up lots of wrong views just, just on account of that very simple thing in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, instead of, eh, going back to the rules,
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, very much.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, when you say meditation, your immediate mind already thinks it's some sort of ecstatic absorption somewhere in some jhāna or some realm.
[SPEAKER_03]: But even jhānas are like, you know, he enters in a biased jhāna and then, whether he extends his arm, whether he walks, whether he goes to eat the food, his mind remains unaffected by things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's in the supras.
[SPEAKER_03]: But not according to the modern ideas of what jhāna is, when you kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gone, basically, motionless, like a rock or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can we now go back to this impermanent nature of six senses?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the impermanence of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, you can be reading in intuitive things and you kind of have to start like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you want even that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any understanding of the relevant nature, you want to be discerning it from things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you know what you're supposed to look for, but you want to find it there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a kind of... it's like, as I said, things by themselves can't teach you, but just your own thinking and explanation, self-explanation, won't teach you either.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to reach a degree of, like, I'm looking for impermanence, how I understood it, what I understood it, I want to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's about recognizing it in your experience, that which you have understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: In this case, impermanence.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, probably the main characteristic, permanence, that I could sort of use, that you could probably relate to, is the recognition that whenever you step into that situation properly, you will always find your body as already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means you have actually no say in its appearance, in its persistence.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the important thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's another thing that
[SPEAKER_03]: The people who don't do mindfulness correctly cannot understand the phenomenon of endurance.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think we spoke about it before.
[SPEAKER_03]: When Buddha says, arising is manifested, ceasing is manifested, or phenomena in general, changing while standing or enduring is manifested.
[SPEAKER_03]: So people usually change the order of how... because the Buddha said, arising is manifested, ceasing is manifested, changing while standing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_03]: Other people say, arising is manifested, changing while standing is manifested, ceasing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can see how it becomes linear.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see things arising, you see things persisting, you see things disappearing, you see things... And that leaves the sense of self out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Completely.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not... that's not based on mindfulness, that kind of view.
[SPEAKER_03]: No matter how much mindfulness you try to put in it, it won't work.
[SPEAKER_03]: What you're going to find is things already there, which means you're going to find things already persisting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means it's the enduring, the third aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the most fundamental aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can see, if something is arising, if something is increasing in its presence, it remains the same while changing.
[SPEAKER_03]: If something is fading out, if something is ceasing, if something is decreasing in its presence, it remains the same while fading out, while changing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize that arising or ceasing, existing or changing is already present in those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how you learn to not interfere with things.
[SPEAKER_03]: They endure on their own, because they have a reason on their own.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's hard, hard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you, can you speak a little bit more?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, I'm planning to, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the point is, by recognizing that things have a reason on their own, or recognizing that whatever you find in this situation that you step into, you already find it there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: Either increasing in its presence, or decreasing in its presence.
[SPEAKER_03]: Either way, it's persisting while changing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just a different direction, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, can you actually see something arising?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't see the first thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't see the first point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, no, now there it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there will be two separate things.
[SPEAKER_03]: First, no, that's a one reason thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, something else, that's another.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, every change, every arising, every ceasing, is abrupt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what Nirmala was talking about as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's abrupt.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Abrupt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you just find it as arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have been... Or you just find it as ceasing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all the time you are basically in that first phase or that middle phase...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're just changing directions, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why arising... That's why often it's kind of omitted sometimes when it says... Oh, and then he remained contemplating arising and falling of the five aggregates and he became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because arising and falling is persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he remains seeing things correctly
[SPEAKER_03]: As a situation, a reason beforehand, not interfering, not appropriating, for the amount of time necessary for the mind to become pure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you say that every arising and ceasing is a breath, and it's like two different experiences.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just finding... As you find your situation, you find it either arising, or you find it either ceasing, depending what's the main, sort of, color, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you cannot break it in the way that you compare your
[SPEAKER_03]: No, because then, the experience with previous experience means, in your background, the both thing together are now one experience that you're thinking about and you're not seeing it as such.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what it means also, like a kālika, timeless.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't involve time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because no matter how much time it's involved in terms of its increasing in its presence or decreasing, while remaining the same and simultaneously with that kind of timely timeline of a thing, simultaneously, thing keeps the identity of itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's no time involved between those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what you start seeing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And seeing an identity of a thing, it's nothing other than seeing a nature of a thing, which is nothing other than seeing dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because dhamma means nature, dhamma means the nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you basically observe this, and you're not changing by standing, cannot happen that you think that it's stable, it's something... Yeah, because you're observing it, and that's already a mistake.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't observe it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can find it in that situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you step back and you find yourself in the situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you learn.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's all about learning how to step back and stay back, without over-intending it and making it in front of you again.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what the development of mind is, like 101.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how to do it?
[SPEAKER_03]: By stepping back and by trying to clarify as much as possible what stepping back entails, what you're supposed to discern, what you're supposed to find.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you do it long enough, then it will become more normal to see, to find things, as opposed to overly intend things and put them in front of you, as that which you think things are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's still formal thinking, but not that forward thinking, so to speak, which is usually what people think thinking is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's... it's on that level what impermanence is, because you already find a thing that isn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have every... and you see, you can't even conceive where it would have come from.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because even that, as in a recent experience, you already find has come from.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, just the notion of it came from somewhere, becomes redundant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, you stop conceiving things as in, out, apart, same, different, both same and different, neither same or different, none of them, none of those things continues to apply, eventually, for another act.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because, as you said, you are always in a... in a situation, you cannot actually escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, with this bodhi, and then you just, she said, step back, and you just see that the bodhi is there, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always, the whole life, it's there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why, by practicing that mindfulness, you start to develop what Jñānavīrā was talking about, cittanimitta, the sign of the mind, the sign of that phenomena, the sign of the phenomena of the experience as a whole, which is where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your mind is where perception and feeling is simultaneously present, which is pretty much, as background as it can be.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, grasping the sign of that, basically, by seeing that actually you're always in the situation, you will stop assuming the existence of any notion of self or control or master, independent of any situation, which is what attavāda is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Assuming yourself independent of the five aggregates, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: assuming yourself independent of the situation as a whole.
[SPEAKER_03]: Assuming the self as external to everything, the master, the creator.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you realize that even when you have that assumption, you have it within the situation upon which has
[SPEAKER_03]: Which has arisen beforehand.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize even that doesn't make sense anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, having the self-view stops making sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you can't have self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it always comes afterwards.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What it's just, it's just, the mind cannot engage in it anymore, because it's just seen as a fully, complete, completely contradictory.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I understand it well, the point is to correctly grasp this, let's say, practice,
[SPEAKER_03]: Simultaneously to that, to keep sort of studying the meaning of the suttas or the instruction, or the instruction that you have faith in.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can be a contemporary instruction, but instruction that you have faith in, not like any, because most of it won't lead you this way.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will send you, like, just along your forward thinking, either through meditation technique or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to keep, sort of, enriching your understanding of what you're supposed to recognize.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the wider the basis, the more information you have, the easier it's going to be to see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it seems very simple from sutras what we are supposed to recognize.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: If your base is wide enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: If your stepping in situation is not corrupted as it is today for most of the people, then, yeah, you wouldn't need necessarily much.
[SPEAKER_03]: All you need is somebody to point you.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look the other way.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you would see it there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why people would sometimes, yeah, just run into the Buddha and hear the teaching and become a sadhāpanna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, well, their notion, their daily experience, their average experience of situation has not been polluted.
[SPEAKER_03]: has not been proliferated as it is today.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can see today, like, even if I talk, or anybody talks about the notion of, like, situation or time or phenomena, it's just like, what?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's some weird philosophy or something, and people dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you look where the people's views are on an average level, it's all about modern science,
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you just assume the public world, the public time, the public space that we all inhabit, and it's all impersonal and everything, and it's constantly changing and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then we all... everything that... Well, see, you assume that as external to your situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you fail to see that any assumption has to remain within that situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So assumption that assumes something external situation is assumption that doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's impossible to assume anything external to situation, because whatever you think of, it's going to be within the situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you cannot never... You cannot step outside of that, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not dwelling on that long enough, you develop all the views that assume outside of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why a vijja is effortless.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just ignoring it, that's impossible to step outside the situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not dwelling on it deep enough, it will make a vijja grow.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't actually have to engage in a vijja in any any other manner.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just ignore it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's called ignorance.
[SPEAKER_03]: And
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why it's not a metaphysical ignorance, hidden somewhere, a secret, that you need to sort of, you know, unlock and a riddle that you need to solve.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's your very attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Every single day, every single moment of your life, when you turn away from your situation that has a reason, that's how you maintain your avijjā, just by looking in the wrong place constantly, by assuming things in the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing I was thinking of today, actually, was
[SPEAKER_01]: We just spoke a lot about the situation, being mindful of it, and stripping one's thinking of yourself in a situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been trying to think about what it exactly means to recognize a situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, obviously, I can give you some words by sitting here, asking you a question in your kriya.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because of the very thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's so easily mystified.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not easy to recognize a situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you might be thinking about it, but then you start doubting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, am I recognizing a situation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or am I recognizing what I create to be a situation?
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you have that doubt, it means, well, that's not a situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because a situation cannot be accessed by doubt either.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you're doubting in a situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can doubt a situation, but if that's also a situation, and if that scene, that which has been seen, cannot be accessed by that doubt, that's being situational, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why you just have to keep doing it, until that doubt of that very situation that you are in, stops touching that situation, so to speak, stops entering it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, again,
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can stop entering, basically, the situation with the doubt by recognizing that that doubt, that very doubt, while you're doubting it, is within the situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's really tricky, because even like I'm now sitting here, it seems to me that now I can do it, what you are talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then the question is, is it really just this?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, because what you probably do is, you just, ah, I am in this situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you kind of, again, originate from the center self, from the center of the I am.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's basically learning how to see things peripherally, without looking at them directly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how you start discerning the situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, whatever you're looking right now, you don't want to move your look away from it, because then it will become another thing you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, while you're looking at it, simultaneously, while you're looking at it, you want to discern other things that you're not looking at directly, which is where your situation is, which is when your body is, your moods, your feelings, the five aggregates, the background.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you look at the background directly,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's on the background anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know if you ever noticed on a kind of a clear summer sky at night, full of stars.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you look at one star, and you look long enough, and then you see lots of stars appearing around it peripherally.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you move your eyes from the central star and look at it, you can't see them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can only see them peripherally.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can only see them if you don't look at them directly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you check that sometimes you see.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, this is the same principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: The background can be revealed rightly only if you don't look at it directly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's like learning how to see.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it says, it's all about one who sees.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because he suddenly saw it like that, and then learned how to see it like... Well, not suddenly saw it like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: He kept trying to see it correctly, eventually built up the right seeing, and now he sees.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because most of the stuff, it's not seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: The background is not seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you are always basically attempting one thing, and just switching from one to another.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's entirely obscured by people's looking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing else obscures it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the only reason you don't see the peripheral stars is because you stare at them directly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if staring at things directly is your mode of existence, that's all you have.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what it is for most people.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I caught myself doing was, like, trying to take stock of things, if I'm literally like, oh, there are feelings, there are perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all in front of me, but that's not it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the situation at the same time is the five agas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, but it's not when you put them in front of them, which is not the agas.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not seeing the situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're seeing what you put in front of you, which means you have left things out.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's keep making that effort to learn how to be mindful of the background while you're looking at different things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Simultaneously present at two layers of experience, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: The context on the general level, like... Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Situation means there's already some meaning, some significance implied in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not like just impersonal listing of, you know, wall, chair, table, that's my situation, space or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the meaning, it's the feeling, it's the mood.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any of that is a background.
[SPEAKER_03]: The five aggregates are a background.
[SPEAKER_03]: The nature of the five aggregates are a background.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're practicing, eh, you know, the Four Foundations of Mindfulness here, taking your awareness of the general situation, eh, and, eh, discerning a particular part,
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, first, the four satipaṭṭhānas can be only done after there's a right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: That doesn't mean you shouldn't be trying them.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think you're actually doing the same until there is the complete clarity in regard to what situation is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, well, not... basically, then, when you think about a posture, you think about the other end of that situation, the background, almost the fundamental
[SPEAKER_03]: The basis.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why you can either think about a bodily posture or the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, he is mindful of the body internally, the body externally, the body internally or externally, or he's mindful of the thought the body is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That the body is there to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that the body is there pertains to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: The far background.
[SPEAKER_03]: His mind is developed to the extent necessary of seeing that background without appropriating it, without making a foreground.
[SPEAKER_03]: To the sufficient extent necessary to completely remove any appropriation of the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: King Coconut is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: The cats are there.
[SPEAKER_03]: The dogs are there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing to do with me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It cannot have anything to do with me, even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you think about that long enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let it endure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whichever way it arises, whichever way it ceases, you let it endure.
[SPEAKER_03]: In a sense, the body is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you will remove any sort of affinity, any sort of
[SPEAKER_03]: Attitude, any assumption, any appropriation of that body as mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in regards mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's already... mind is already included.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because how can you see the background without seeing your mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not like... See, that's a...
[SPEAKER_03]: If you were to think about your body in medical terms, then you would leave the mind out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the question you just asked would be valid.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, where is the mind then?
[SPEAKER_03]: But you can see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you see your body on that background level, as enduring, as in a reason necessary basis for your experience as a whole,
[SPEAKER_03]: Means your mind is already... that's where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't see the background without seeing the mind, because that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where the satipaṭṭhāna sutra tells... when he comes to mind, he just describes the mind in those ambiguous background general terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: He sees his mind as elated, or as depressed, or as expanded, or as light, or as heavy.
[SPEAKER_03]: The background, the mood, the distance, don't speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, as you can see,
[SPEAKER_03]: By thinking the mind is elsewhere, opposed to the body, people don't even see the basic notion of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what cittanimitta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why people cannot get the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because one of the conditions for the right view is cittanimitta.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: The proper phenomenological sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: As it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not as you project it to be.
[SPEAKER_03]: You find your mind there as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: You find the mind expanded, shrunk, depressed, elated, happy, sad,
[SPEAKER_03]: You find it there.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, you find a situation, you find it's in that situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's found on the basis of that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: As everything else is, that's when mindfulness comes first, that's the enlightenment factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: We spoke recently about developing mindfulness of the citta, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what I was, I was also thinking about was, you know, citta, saṃkhāra, vipassana, sīla, viññāṇa, samādhi, pañña, ayoniso, yoniso, cittanimitta, sañña, vedanā, pañña, ayoniso, yoniso, citta, nimitta, sañña, vedanā, pañca, upādāna, khandhā, pañcupādānakkhandhā, nāma, cetanā, pañcupādānakkhand
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you see, it depends on the existence of the particular phenomenon of feeling and the perception that's simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because without those things arising, this shape of the mind, this sort of attitude of the mind, this background of the mind, would have not been developed at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't even conceive it separately.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can just see when the mind means there has to be a feeling, there has to be a perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is it something else?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or can you just reduce it to feeling-perception?
[SPEAKER_03]: Feeling and perception is the basis for the mind, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that mind is something else?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yes, but not something else in terms of elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in the same sense, like, in the same sense, like, when the... Well, you can say feeling, perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feeling and perception, that's what mind is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, mind is not feeling, mind is not perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, as you can see, there is no end to this background, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's infinite.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can see the feeling, and then you can see the perception, and then you can see there is feeling, there is perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, actually, it's infinite in the in the sense of, eh... stepping back.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in the sense of mind development, you could surmount feeling and perception, and then the mind would cease.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there's a station of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's reserved only for those who have right view, who has that discernment of that relationship, of that timeless dependence of these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feeling perception, that's what the mind does.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of similar on a slightly lesser level, so to speak, lower level, where the Buddha said, feeling, perception, intention are inseparable.
[SPEAKER_03]: They cannot possibly occur without each other.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nor can they be conceived apart, but they're not the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that intention is basically where the mind comes down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feeling-perception the mind, or feeling-perception intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Looking back to this thing peripherally, the stepping back, does it mean that you see also your stepping back?
[SPEAKER_03]: You could, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That can become part of it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's the attitude that's present in your situation, that you intended, because you've been reading the dhamma, and so on, and want to practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why vijja, like this destruction of avijja, or arahantship, nibbāna, is dependent upon, directly dependent upon, practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't sound direct, but you can see in this sense, oh, it was because of you,
[SPEAKER_03]: Directly making intentions of stepping back and developing knowledge resulted in arahantship.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because you went there, that's where arahantship was.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it depends upon trying to open the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, because it brings another, basically, another issue of listening to your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Quite clearly, to become an ārya, it cannot happen by chance.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the effort was right, you could have not not realized.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, one cannot actually blame anyone.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just like you're all... For as long as you're alive, functioning with your faculties intact, it's absolutely on you, entirely.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why, that's why, basically, the longer you do it, without the results, you should be more concerned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because what you do is probably not in the right way.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't still lead anywhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, yeah, it's not an easy sort of thing to admit to yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Say, somebody's been sort of making it for 30-40 years, and hasn't arrived at any sort of distinction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, 30 years?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's a lifetime of investment, of commitment and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what are you going to do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you going to scratch the door and start from the beginning?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or are you going to sort of give in to the reputation, comfort,
[SPEAKER_03]: recognition, gain, which you developed for the 30 years, and then sort of just say, no, no, no, it's about this.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about getting anywhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about developing distinction.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about becoming sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about just being here and now, present, body-mind, whatnot.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what you hear from people.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it also seems that the more you practice one way, more and more difficult,
[SPEAKER_02]: But you should also recognize that if you see even a little bit of value in what I'm saying, that's already a big step forward.
[SPEAKER_02]: That already means you already get some sense of the direction where I'm coming from.
[SPEAKER_03]: And for most people, it would just go over their head.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just like...
[SPEAKER_03]: They either think it's... Oh, yeah, of course, I already know that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But they think, what are you talking about?
[SPEAKER_03]: It makes completely no sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: Dhamma is not about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means it's either overly or or underly, sort of, looked for.
[SPEAKER_03]: They never kind of can see it at the right level, where it actually is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you even have a faint notion of...
[SPEAKER_03]: There might be something there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's already quite a big opening.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, it's up to you to make the effort and pursue it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you don't do it, then it's just going to stay a possibility for an opening.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's not the actual opening.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, of course it's hard.
[SPEAKER_03]: If it were easy, you wouldn't need a Buddha.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what the Buddha said to him.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's because of... Like, Ananda said, oh, it's so simple.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's so clear to me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, no, don't say that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's so hard.
[SPEAKER_03]: People remain bound for eons and eons and eons, like countless eons of e
[SPEAKER_03]: Just because of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just because they cannot discern their direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it cannot be discerned by yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if you succeed it, you become sāmasambuddha.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can see how insane that is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you're incomprehensible.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, oh, who am I to praise the Buddha?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because they would realize the extent of somebody, like, what they know, because someone else's instruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like somebody found it out by themselves.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like,
[SPEAKER_03]: How is that impossible?
[SPEAKER_03]: It verges on the impossible, but not quite.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then somebody does it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize that's just... you can't even praise that.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is beyond you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's like coming from the Arahants in the sutras.
[SPEAKER_03]: Who am I to praise the Buddha?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because even with instruction, it's like virtually impossible for most people.
[SPEAKER_03]: Imagine somebody finding that out for himself.
[SPEAKER_03]: The extent of that effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: Question the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, we covered it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind is māna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's basically māna would be your reasoning, your intellect, your foreground of your thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you said also that it's like a bullet.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's what citta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what the
[SPEAKER_03]: Citta, mind as citta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mano is in the same sense your eyes, a foreground, what you're thinking right away, what you're looking right away, what you're smelling right away.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where mano is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to have mano determined to point in the direction to look beyond it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can have particular thoughts that are seen in the general situation and the sight of the general situation, the images of the general situation seen correctly, that's the level of citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Those are the phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the mind can be object to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like mind objects and mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you need, in simple terms, think of mind as mano.
[SPEAKER_03]: Think of that being like thoughts that are concerned with the five senses, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not the thoughts that are concerned with the background of it, with the nature of it, with any of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: The reflexive thoughts in regard to it, they would not be the mano.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what about abstract thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there concern about sense domain?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, we are not concerned with sense domain, like we are thinking about whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like?
[SPEAKER_02]: Something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Such as?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know, about...
[SPEAKER_02]: Nature of feelings?
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe, or maybe about the nature of universe.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's something we experience through senses, the universe.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in the sense domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aha, so...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're thinking about the nature of it, then there will be like, māna would be the actual thoughts in regard to the sense of the mind, but the nature will be a reflection upon that particular sense of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you don't really have to worry about much of a distinction between mind and māna and citta and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: All you have to do is just be sone.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we think that the most essential essence is to learn this
[SPEAKER_03]: Seeing things peripherally, to step back and not to be involved with particular... Yeah, not to disregard the particular either, but to learn how to see beyond it, while particular is still present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's how your mind expands, literally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because mind is bound whatever you're looking at, whatever you smell, whatever occupies your attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what people see.
[SPEAKER_03]: And learning, while that's present, to see what's beyond it, simultaneously present while that is there, makes your mind bigger.
[SPEAKER_03]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_02]: And how much you can do it, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you keep it continuously?
[SPEAKER_03]: Indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_03]: The growth can be indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you can do it to the extent necessary for the final knowledge, as Satipaṭṭhāna Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it seems that probably at the beginning, it's only like, when you remember, you just go here and there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just being dragged each time, whenever something new arises.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, discerning that peripheral background correctly as a phenomena, you can also... you can also arrive at it with the... by the recognition of the phenomenon of enduring of an arisen thing, or of the thing that's ceasing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that means you kind of have to stay with it, but not fully particularly into it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you have to see it changing while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to see it on two levels, so to speak, simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why you can approach it through that angle.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the three, the three sort of aspects in the manifest.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or just arising, or just... Or something said, oh, there is a monk who is very proficient in arising.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's enough for our country.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is a monk who is very proficient in ceasing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because he uses the persisting while changing,
[SPEAKER_03]: Because ceasing is manifesting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Arising is manifesting.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not like ceasing is the actual cessation that you witness, a destruction of things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because otherwise, if it's a destruction of a thing, then that's what's manifesting, that's what has arisen.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can see that destruction can take place only on a particular level.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like a thing being destroyed, like changing a shape, still remaining a thing, or change becoming a different thing, because it's not the same thing from before, but it's still a thing that came
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, it's not... cessation does not mean the ending.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just means a different direction from arising, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Increasing or ceasing, either way, existing or changing.
[SPEAKER_03]: But usually, people just tend to quickly bundle together.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cessation means ending.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, I can see these branches falling down, trees breaking, everything is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: That experience has a reason for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: The experience of a tree being broken down, that's what has arisen in your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's actually arising, you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't basically look outside, you just watch your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why, like, we're creating a distinction saying, the impermanence that the Buddha was talking about is the impermanence that, if understood, frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, like, the trees being destroyed makes no difference to you, unless you're emotionally bound with those trees, and then you suffer on contact.
[SPEAKER_03]: But not because they're being destroyed, but because you're attached to them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the cause of suffering is not the destruction of things.
[SPEAKER_03]: The cause is your craving in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you would still, even then, look at the wrong place, if you assume the cessation as a destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, our assumption we could think of, for example, correct me if I'm saying wrong, is, okay, there's a situation that I find myself in, living, and within that,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is also a thought of the body in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even just the basic thought of there is the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you recognize, you understand, firstly, the nature of matter, of consciousness, basically, that, you know, there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all you can have is thoughts, images, dhammas.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what things are.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, well, you can also just, in the... let's say you're mindful of the situation properly, or at least, sort of, sufficiently.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you have a thought like, ah, this body is there, well, see where that thought is directed.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is it aiming at?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is it referring to?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is that you're trying to designate by that thought?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's often left unclear to people.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you just end up carrying on the assumption they were completely gratuitous to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: But because you never looked at their gratuity, you keep keeping them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You keep maintaining them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, when you say, of this body... Well, what am I referring to specifically?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do I refer to the bits that I see with my eyes?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or do I feel this... the feeling of touch of the chair and the table I'm leaning on?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, or, or the itch, or you feel that they refer to the heat, or the energy, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: What are you referring to?
[SPEAKER_03]: And, just find out what you're referring to, in that general situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, what, what, what is this being directed at, when I say... Because, it has to be directed upon something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, if this thing hasn't been arisen at all, you wouldn't be able to pull it in any terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, the failure you can pull it, sometimes means you are having some sort of notion of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it is possible to step back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Theoretically, then, any kind of thing you're referring to, so long as you understand that the actual matter of the body is not that which you are pointing to, could be taken sufficiently to say, this is the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry, say again?
[SPEAKER_03]: Which matter are you referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as you understand that whatever you're designating as body is not the matter of the body.